this video explains how the three types
of chemical bonding work first ionic
bonding between metal and non-metal
atoms for example sodium and chlorine
all metal atoms generally have between
one and three electrons in their outer
shell for example sodium has one in its
outer shell shown as a cross non-metal
atoms generally have between four and
eight electrons in their outer shell
chlorine for example has seven shown as
dots but all atoms want a full outer
shell so the metal and non-metal atoms
do a deal the metal sodium atom gives
its electron away and the non-metal
chlorine atom receives it now they both
have full outer shells but where does
the ionic bond come from both atoms were
neutral but after trading the electron
the sodium is now a positive ion and the
chlorine is now a negative ion the
oppositely charged ions attract causing
the ionic bond many ions attract to form
a giant lattice structure ionic
compounds have interesting properties
because ionic bonds are strong and act
in all directions in the lattice it
takes a lot of energy to break the ionic
bonds giving ionic compounds high
melting
points second Cove valent bonding
between non-metal atoms let's look at
water again all atoms want a full outer
shell oxygen has six outer shell
electrons but needs eight hydrogen has
one electron in its outer shell but
needs two but rather than swap electrons
like ionic bonding coent compounds share
electrons the oxygen atom shares one
pair of electrons with each hydrogen
atom each hydrogen now has two electrons
and the oxygen has eight all of them are
happy so where does the bond come from
the shared pairs of electrons are
negative and the nuclei of all atoms are
positive the attraction between them is
the Cove valent Bond and like ionic
bonds they're very strong water is one
of three kinds of calent compound called
a simple calent compound although calent
bonds are strong the forces between the
small molecules are weak so it takes
little energy to break these weak
intermolecular forces meaning that water
and other simple calent compounds have
very low boiling points however giant
calent compounds like diamond have very
high melting points due to the calent
bonds and finally we have metallic
bonding between metal atoms such as iron
ion has two electrons on its outer shell
But Metal at work as a group and share
their electrons between them the
electrons form a sea of delocalized
electrons which are free to roam
throughout the giant lattice where does
the bonding come from well the positive
nuclei are all held together by the ca
of delocalized electrons like a strong
glue the bonding is very strong meaning
that metal generally has very high
melting
points so these are the three types of
bonding for a closer look at calent
compounds with some examples see the
following video and don't forget to like
And subscribe